Arpit Gupta

Research Interests

As a systems researcher, I design and build *flexible*, *scalable*, and *trustworthy* systems that solve real-world problems at the intersection of networking, security, and machine learning. Specifically, I am interested in developing self-driving networks that provide highly available, reliable, performant, and secure network connectivity at lower costs to under-served communities.

Education

August 2018 Princeton University, Ph.D., Computer Science.

Dissertation: Flexible and Scalable Systems for Network Management

Adviser: Nick Feamster

Honorary Mention, SIGCOMM Dissertation Award

Spring 2016 **Princeton University**, M.A., Computer Science.

Spring 2013 NC State University, M.S., Computer Science.

Spring 2009 Indian Institute of Technology, Roorkee, B. Tech., Electronics & Comm.

Professional Experience

Summer 2019— University of California, Santa Barbara, Assistant Professor, Santa Barbara, CA.

2018–2019 Columbia University, Postdoctoral Research Scientist, New York, NY.

2015–2018 Princeton University, Research Assistant, Princeton, NJ.

Summer 2016 Microsoft Research, Research Intern, Redmond, WA.

2013–2014 Georgia Tech, Research Assistant, Princeton, NJ.

2011–2012 NC State University, Research Assistant, Raleigh, NC.

Summer 2011 Google, Software Engineering Intern, Mountain View, CA.

Spring 2010 Indian Institute of Science, Project Assistant, Bangalore, India.

Awards

- 2022 ACM SIGCOMM IMC Distinguished Paper Award (Long)
- 2022 IETF/IRTF Applied Networking Prize
- 2022 Honorable Mention, ACM CCS Best Paper
- 2018 Honorable Mention, SIGCOMM Dissertation Award
- 2017 Best Paper Award winner, ACM SOSR
- 2017 Facebook Fellowship finalist
- 2016 USENIX "Best of the Rest" Paper Award for Best Paper in all USENIX Conferences
- 2016 USENIX Community Contribution Award, USENIX/ACM Symposium on Networked Systems Design and Implementation
- 2015 Facebook Fellowship finalist
- 2013 Internet-2 Innovation Award winner
- 2013 Meissner Fellowship, Purdue University (declined)
- 2010 College of Engineering Fellowship, North Carolina State University

Publications

Conferences

- [1] Udit Paul, Vinothini Gunasekaran, Jiamo Liu, Tejas Narechania, Arpit Gupta, and Elizabeth Belding. Decoding the Divide: Analyzing Disparities in Broadband Plans Offered by Major US ISPs. In *ACM SIGCOMM*, 2023.
- [2] Fuheng Zhao, Punnal Ismail Khan, Divyakant Agrawal, Amr El Abbadi, Arpit Gupta, and Zaoxing Liu. Panakos: Chasing the tails for multidimensional data streams. In *International Conference on Very Large Data Bases (VLDB)*, 2023.
- [3] Arthur S Jacobs, Roman Beltiukov, Walter Willinger, Ronaldo A Ferreira, Arpit Gupta, and Lisandro Z Granville. Ai/ml for network security: The emperor has no clothes. In ACM Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS), 2022. IETF/IRTF Applied Networking Research Prize (ANRP), Best Paper Award (Honorary Mention).
- [4] Congcong Miao, Minggang Chen, Arpit Gupta, Zili Meng, Lianjin Ye, Jingyu Xiao, Jie Chen, Zekun He, Xulong Luo, Jilong Wang, and Heng Yu. Detecting Ephemeral Optical Events with OpTel. In *USENIX Symposium on Networked Systems Design and Implementation (NSDI)*, 2022.
- [5] Udit Paul, Jiamo Liu, Arpit Gupta, Mengyang Gu, and Elizabeth Belding. The Importance of Contextualization of Crowdsourced Active Speed Test Measurements. In ACM SIGCOMM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC), 2022.
 Distinguished Paper Award.
- [6] Vivek Adarsh, Michael Nekrasov, Udit Paul, Alexander Ermakov, Arpit Gupta, Morgan Vigil-Hayes, Ellen W Zegura, and Elizabeth M Belding. Coverage is Not Binary: Quantifying Mobile Broadband Quality in Urban, Rural and Tribal Contexts. In International Conference on Computer Communications and Networks (ICCCN), 2021.
- [7] Vivek Adarsh, Michael Nekrasov, Udit Paul, Alexander Ermakov, Arpit Gupta, Morgan Vigil-Hayes, Ellen W Zegura, and Elizabeth M Belding. Too Late for Playback: Estimation of Video Stream Quality in Rural and Urban Contexts. In *Passive and Active Measurement Conference (PAM)*, 2021.
- [8] Todd Arnold, Ege Gürmeriçliler, Georgia Essig, Arpit Gupta, Matt Calder, Vasileios Giotsas, and Ethan Katz-Bassett. (How Much) Does a Private WAN Improve Cloud Performance? In *IEEE Conference on Computer Communications (INFOCOM)*, 2020.
- [9] Arpit Gupta, Rob Harrison, Ankita Pawar, Marco Canini, Nick Feamster, Jennifer Rexford, and Walter Willinger. Sonata: Query-Driven Network Telemetry. In ACM SIGCOMM, 2018.
- [10] Robert MacDavid, Rüdiger Birkner, Ori Rottenstreich, Arpit Gupta, Nick Feamster, and Jennifer Rexford. Concise Encoding of Flow Attributes in SDN Switches. In ACM Symposium on SDN Research (SOSR), 2017.
 Best Paper Award.
- [11] Arpit Gupta, Robert MacDavid, Rüdiger Birkner, Marco Canini, Nick Feamster, Jennifer Rexford, and Laurent Vanbever. An Industrial-Scale Software Defined Internet Exchange Point. In USENIX Symposium on Networked Systems Design and Implementation (NSDI), 2016.

Community Award.

- [12] Hyojoon Kim, Joshua Reich, **Arpit Gupta**, Muhammad Shahbaz, Nick Feamster, and Russ Clark. Kinetic: Verifiable Dynamic Network Control. In *USENIX Symposium on Networked Systems Design and Implementation (NSDI)*, 2015.
- [13] Arpit Gupta, Laurent Vanbever, Muhammad Shahbaz, Sean Patrick Donovan, Brandon Schlinker, Nick Feamster, Jennifer Rexford, Scott Shenker, Russ Clark, and Ethan Katz-Bassett. SDX: A Software Defined Internet Exchange. In ACM SIGCOMM, 2014. Internet2 Innovation Award.
- [14] Arpit Gupta, Jeongki Min, and Injong Rhee. Wifox: Scaling wifi performance for large audience environments. In ACM Conference on Emerging Networking Experiments and Technologies (CoNEXT), 2012.

Workshops & Short Papers

- [15] Todd Arnold, Matt Calder, **Arpit Gupta**, Italo Cunha, Michael Schapira, and Ethan Katz-Bassett. Beating BGP is Harder than We Thought. In *ACM HotNets*, 2019.
- [16] Hyojoon Kim and **Arpit Gupta**. Ontas: Flexible and scalable online network traffic anonymization system. In *ACM SIGCOMM NetAI*, 2019.
- [17] **Arpit Gupta**, Chris MacStoker, and Walter Willinger. An Effort to Democratize Networking Research in the Era of AI/ML. In *ACM HotNets*, 2019.
- [18] Rob Harrison, Qizhe Cai, **Arpit Gupta**, and Jennifer Rexford. Network-Wide Heavy Hitter Detection with Commodity Switches. In *ACM Symposium on SDN Research* (SOSR), 2018.
- [19] Rüdiger Birkner, **Arpit Gupta**, Nick Feamster, and Laurent Vanbever. SDX-Based Flexibility or Internet Correctness?: Pick Two! In *ACM Symposium on SDN Research* (SOSR), 2017.
- [20] **Arpit Gupta**, Rüdiger Birkner, Marco Canini, Nick Feamster, Chris Mac-Stoker, and Walter Willinger. Network Monitoring as a Streaming Analytics Problem. In *ACM Workshop on Hot Topics in Networks (HotNets)*, 2016.
- [21] **Arpit Gupta**, Nick Feamster, and Laurent Vanbever. Authorizing Network Control at Software Defined Internet Exchange Points. In *ACM Symposium on SDN Research* (SOSR), 2016.
- [22] **Arpit Gupta**, Matt Calder, Nick Feamster, Marshini Chetty, Enrico Calandro, and Ethan Katz-Bassett. Peering at the Internet's Frontier: A First Look at ISP Interconnectivity in Africa. In *Passive and Active Network Measurement (PAM)*, 2014.

Research Proposals and Grants

IMR: MT: NetFlex: A Flexible Scalable & Privacy-Preserving Network Measurement Platform to Iteratively Collect Multi-modal Multi-view Network Data from Access Networks.

Sponsor: NSF

Investigator(s): A. Gupta Amount: \$ 600 k for 2 years.

Awarded: Fall 2023.

IMR: RI-P: Programmable Closed-loop Measurement Platform for Last-Mile Networks.

Sponsor: NSF

Investigator(s): A. Gupta and N. Feamster

Amount: \$ 100 k for 2 years.

Awarded: Fall 2022.

IMR: MM-1A: ADDRESS: Augment, Denoise and Debias Crowdsourced Measurements for Statistical Synthesis of Internet Access Characterization.

Sponsor: NSF

Investigator(s): E. Belding, A. Gupta, and M. Gu

Amount: \$ 600 k for 3 years.

Awarded: Fall 2022.

CC^* Integration-Large: Democratizing Networking Research in the Era of AI/ML.

Sponsor: NSF

Investigator(s): A. Gupta, T. Gupta, E. Belding, and N. Feamster

Amount: \$ 1 M for 3 years. Awarded: Fall 2021.

CC* Integration-Large: Bringing Code to Data: A Collaborative Approach to Democratizing Internet Data Science.

Sponsor: NSF

Investigator(s): R. Durairajan, A. Gupta, R. Rezai, J. Miyake, and D. Teach

Amount: \$ 1 M for 3 years.

Awarded: Fall 2021.

Scaling Network Security with PISA Switches.

Sponsor: Verizon

Investigator(s): A. Gupta Amount: \$ 200 k for 2 years. Awarded: December 2019.

Self-Driving Broadband Networks.

Sponsor: Beegol Inc. Investigator(s): A. Gupta Amount: \$ 35 k for 1 year. Awarded: July 2020.

Workshop on Next-G Mobile Security.

Sponsor: NSF

Investigator(s): A. Gupta Amount: \$ 49 k for 1 year. Awarded: July 2020.

MLWiNS: RL-based Self-driving Wireless Network Management System for QoE Optimization.

Sponsor: NSF

Investigator(s): A. Gupta (PI), E. Belding, Y. Wang

Amount: \$ 560 k for 3 years.

Awarded: July 2020.

MLWiNS: RL-based Self-driving Wireless Network Management System for QoE Optimization.

Sponsor: Intel

Investigator(s): A. Gupta (PI), E. Belding, Y. Wang

Amount: \$ 280 k for 3 years.

Awarded: July 2020.

Presentations

Making the "Net" Work: Flexible and Scalable Systems for Network Management

Universities: Texas A&M University (02/18), UC Santa Barbara (02/18), Northeastern University (03/18), University of Virginia (03/18), University of Minnesota (04/18), University of Toronto (04/18)

Sonata: Query-Driven Streaming Network Telemetry

Conferences: ACM HotNets (11/16), NANOG 70 (05/17), P4 Workshop (05/17)

Industry: Comcast (12/16), NIKSUN Inc. (06/17), AT&T (10/17)

Universities: New England Networking & Systems Day, Boston University (10/16)

iSDX: An Industrial-Scale Software Defined IXP

Conferences: USENIX NSDI (03/16), USENIX ATC (06/16), GENI Network Innovators Community Event (12/16)

Industry: AT&T (10/15), Project Endeavour (10/15), Corsa (11/15), CloudRouter (01/16), Open Networking Foundation Webinar (04/16), Appfest (05/16)

Universities: Networked Systems Laboratory, USC (08/15))

Authorizing Network Control at Software Defined IXPs

Conferences: ACM SOSR (03/16) Industry: Verisign Inc. (08/15)

SDX: A Software Defined Internet Exchange

Conferences: ACM SIGCOMM (08/14), GENI Engineering Conference 20 (06/14), NANOG 59 (10/13), OpenIX Summit (04/15))

Industry: Facebook Inc. (08/14), Microsoft (08/14)

Universities: NetSeminar, Stanford University (10/14)

Peering at the Internet's Frontier

Conferences: Workshop on Passive and Active Measurements (03/14)

WiFox: Scaling WiFi Performance for Large Audience

Conferences: ACM SIGCOMM CoNEXT (12/12)

Universities: Duke University (10/12), UNC Chapel Hill (10/12)

Professional Activities

Program Committee Chair

- 2021 ACM SIGCOMM Artifact Evaluation Committee, Virtual
- 2020 ACM SIGCOMM Student Research Competition, Virtual
- 2019 ACM SIGCOMM Workshop on Network Meets AI & ML (NetAI), Beijing, CN Organizing Committee Chair
- 2023 NSF Workshop on "Bridging the Divide: Answering Internet Policy Questions with Cutting-Edge Network Measurement Algorithms, Datasets, and Platforms", Berkeley, CA
- 2023 SIGMETRICS Workshop on "Measurements for Self-driving Networks", Orlando, FL
- 2020 NSF Workshop on NextG Security, Virtual
- 2019 NSF Workshop on "Measurements for Self-driving Networks", Princeton, NJ

Program Committee Member

- 2024 ACM SIGMETRICS
- 2023 ACM SIGCOMM IMC
- 2021-24 USENIX Networked System Design and Implementation (NSDI)
- 2020-21 ACM SIGCOMM
 - 2020 USENIX Networked System Design and Implementation (NSDI)
 - 2019 ACM Conference on Emerging Networking Experiments and Technologies (CoNEXT)
 - 2019 ACM SIGCOMM Symposium on SDN Research (SOSR)
 - 2018 ACM SIGCOMM Workshop on Self-Driving Networks

Organizing Committee Member

- 2018 NSF Workshop on Self-driving Networks, Princeton $\underline{\text{Panelist}}$
- 2016 GENI Network Innovators Community Event 2016
- 2016 CITP Conference on Global Internet Interconnection

External Reviewer

- 2019 Privacy Enhancing Technologies Symposium (PETS)
- 2017 ACM SIGCOMM
- 2016 IEEE International Conference on Network Protocol (ICNP)
- 2014 USENIX Networked System Design and Implementation (NSDI)

Journal Reviewer

IEEE/ACM Transactions on: Networking (TNET), Mobile Computing (TMC), Network Science and Engineering (TNSE), Computer Networks Journal (COMNET), Photonic Network Communications (PNET) Journal of Network and Computer Applications (JNAC), Cloud Computing, Special Issue: Middleware and Middlecloud (CCMSI), International Journal of Network Management (IJNM)

Teaching

Instructor

- 2020-2022 ML For Networked Systems, (CS 293N), UCSB
 - 2020-23 Advanced Topics in Internet Computing,, (CS 176C), UCSB
 - 2021-23 Programmable Networks, (CS 176B), UCSB

Course Development

- Spring 2016 Securing Cyberspace with Big Data (COS 598E), Princeton University
- Summer 2015 Software Defined Networking, Coursera
 - Fall 2014 Software Defined Networking (CS 4270), Georgia Tech
- Summer 2014 Software Defined Networking, Coursera

Guest Lecture

- Fall 2017 Advanced Computer Networks (COS 561), Princeton University
- Spring 2017 Computer Networks (COS 461), Princeton University

■ Ph.D. Students

Current

- Fall 2018 * Udit Paul, UCSB, Ph.D. (co-advised with Prof. Belding)
- Fall 2019 * Sanjay Chandrasekaran, UCSB, Ph.D.
- Fall 2021 * Roman Beltiukov, UCSB, Ph.D.
- Fall 2021 * Punnak Ismail Khan, UCSB, Ph.D.
- Fall 2022 * Satyandra Guthula, UCSB, Ph.D.